<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the variance betweene the Pope, and the segniory of Venice with the proceedings and present state thereof. VVhereunto is annexed a defence of the Venetians, written by an Italian doctor of Diuinitie, against the censure of Paulus Quintus, proouing the nullitie thereof by Holy Scriptures, canons, and catholique Doctors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849434</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 931:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the variance betweene the Pope, and the segniory of Venice with the proceedings and present state thereof. VVhereunto is annexed a defence of the Venetians, written by an Italian doctor of Diuinitie, against the censure of Paulus Quintus, proouing the nullitie thereof by Holy Scriptures, canons, and catholique Doctors.</title>
                  <author>Manfredi, Fulgenzio, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66, 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An ecclesiastical controversy between the Pope and Leonardo Donato, doge of Venice.</note>
                  <note>An Italian doctor of Diuinitie = Fulgenzio Manfredi?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paul --  V, --  Pope, 1552-1621.</term>
               <term>Donato, Leandro, 1536-1612.</term>
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  History --  Papal Interdict, 1606-1607 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14581:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14581:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE Variance betweene the Pope, and the Segniory
of VENICE, <hi>With the proceedings and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> ſtate thereof.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> written
by an Italian doctor of Diuinitie, Againſt the <hi>Cenſure of</hi> Paulus
Quintus, <hi>Proouing the Nullitie thereof by Holy Scriptures, Canons, and
Catholique Doctors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:14581:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14581:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENICE,</hi> Setting foorth the variance
<hi>betweene the Pope and</hi> that State: <hi>Declaring the cauſes,
procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> and preſent iſſue thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I reckon my ſelfe ſo much in your debt, for your laſt
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning matters lately fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len out in England, ſome in
queſtion, ſome in action, and all worthy of obſeruation, As that I can do
no leſſe, then render ſome part of requitall, by the returne vnto you
againe, of a true Relation concerning that memorable accident here with vs in
<hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> ſo famous in ſpeech, (as ſounding <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14581:3"/> in
euery eare) ſo weighty in deed, (as draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on great conſequences,) and
ſo remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in conſideration, (as that our Engliſh Nation may make
good vſe thereof) which in this my plaineſt manner, affecting more
<hi>veritatis candorem,</hi> then <hi>ornamenta artis,</hi> I offer to your
peruſall; praying aſwell your pardon, where I do not ſatisfie your
curious eye, as your acceptation of my good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though I come ſhort
of your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation.</p>
            <p>I hold it not neceſſary to diſcourſe of the wealth, power,
or amplitude of this Segnio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, referring you to ſundry copious and exact
Treatiſes, written as it were to the life of this Subiect, which deſcribe
as in a Mappe or Table, euery matter obſeruable for a requiſite knowledge
thereof. It may ſuffice therefore, for the opening of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient entrance
into the Narration which I haue vndertaken to deliuer vnto you, That you doe
conceiue thus much: The <hi>Venetian</hi> State is at this preſent, (as
alſo of long continuance) very ſtrong, and not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to be ſhaken,
their adminiſtration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14581:3"/> fuller of Wiſedome then
Force, and yet withall of ſuch Force, as (with a Wiſdome not ouer haſtie
to prouoke others) is well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to defend and maintaine their owne both honour
and right. Their Territories are large and fertile, though ſubiect to the
affront of more mighty Monarchs; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the meaneſt (in courſe of
hoſtilitie) may well ſeeme ſo dangerous, as they are not ſlightly to
bee feared. And therefore it much concerneth that State, to ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a
circumſpect carriage of it ſelfe, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing actes of enmitie with
ſuch their neere neighbours, or miniſtring to any of them any vniuſt or
offenſiue occaſions. It hath euermore eſpecially, and with ſtricteſt
correſpondence, (if not with ouermuch addicted obedience) aſſured it
ſelfe vnto his Holineſſe, caſting their ancre, aſwell of their
ſafetie in worldly diſtreſſes, as alſo of their hope of eternall
bleſſedneſſe, into the deepe and deceiueable ſands of the Romiſh
diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</p>
            <p>This knot of league betweene the Pope and the <hi>Venetians,</hi>
which oftentimes ſome <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14581:4"/> great oppoſing Potentates
endeuored to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is now of late (I will not ſay vpon an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, but
rather vpon a very eſſentiall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury offered by the Pope) ſo cut
aſunder, as that many ſtitches, and much labour of the beſt apted
compoſers, will not eaſily faſten or draw it together againe. If you aske
me, what miracle-maker hath had his hand in the working of this wonder; I
muſt firſt anſwere you ſeriouſly, that GOD hath his times, and meanes
to bring to paſſe his fore-decreed purpoſes; And vſeth out of ſmall
beginnings, to draw the threed at length to his owne determined concluſion.
Next, I will tell you merily, That it is both the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh propoſition
prohibiting Prieſts to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Popiſh practiſe of couering their
habite of ſinne, vnder their habit Clericall, that was the Factor of tearing
aſunder ſo ſure friends. And laſtly, take this for a <hi>Maxime,</hi>
That the ſuperlatiue ſupremacie of the Popes ouer-awing power, endureth not
any touch in the leaſt part of his body Eccleſiaſticall, no not in the
very heele or little toe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14581:4"/>In the meditation whereof, and before I enter
into my promiſed Declaration, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conteine my ſelfe, from powring out
my prayers to GOD, that he will bleſſe this the <hi>Venetians</hi>
encounter of the Romiſh pride, with the like ſucceſſe, which it
pleaſed him to giue to the like aduenture, in the time of King <hi>H.</hi> 8.
when he reuiued the queſtion of the Popes Pontifical decrees, &amp; did eiect
his falſe and ill-gotten Supremacie; by which one blow ſo ſtroken, he
hath left vpon him the print of his fingers euer ſince. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if this
one Capitall point, of his ſtrange, or rather idle Attribute of Power to
diſpoſe of Princes, were truely battered, there would ſuch breaches bee
made vpon him on euery ſide, as he would eaſily part with that which he
accounteth his ſtrongeſt hold. You ſhall ſee how notoriouſly his
Greatneſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlimited Abſoluteneſſe, of <hi>Dixi &amp;
elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus ſum,</hi> diſplaying it ſelfe in his beſt robes and in his
Conſiſtoriall power, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come contemptible, and held as a meere
ſcorne, by his aggrieued neighbour State, bound by vowes to all filiall
duties, and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14581:5"/> vp with the milke of Rome, cloſe at
his doore, in <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelfe, where hee ſheweth foorth all his
pageants of pompe and glory, And that vpon iuſtifiable occaſion, and by
proceedings vnreproueable.</p>
            <p>ABout December laſt, the ſaid free, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and
vndependant State of <hi>Venice,</hi> (finding nothing more neceſſary for
conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, or more eſtimable for dignitie, then to ſuppreſſe and
puniſh enormious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors) did lay the hands of Iuſtice vpon two of their
Cleargie in Clericall habit, the one an Abbot, accuſed of many notorious
crimes; The other a Canon of <hi>Vicenza,</hi> for diſhonouring of a Virgine.
The impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and proſecuting againſt theſe two, was the firſt
ſtimulatory cauſe of ſplene and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, betwixt the Pope and the
Segniorie. The Canoniſts helde the State to ſtand <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi>
Excommunicate, without any Iuridicall proceeding, for this their
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, and Irregular vſurpation of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie beyond their bounds
ouer the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent Cleargie, whom they ought (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) to haue remitted
to the Cenſure of <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14581:5"/> their owne immediate ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>The Clergie thus ſtartled, and all ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with heate and
indignation, poſteth ouer their Aduertiſements of theſe ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
wrongs offered the Church, vnto his Holineſſe; In whoſe Court, and about
whoſe Perſon, they wanted not ſtirring In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to exaſperate his
anger, by other aggrauating ſuggeſtions added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. The
principall Agent that blowed this Fire, is ſuſpected to be the Cardinall
<hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phino,</hi> one of their owne Nobilitie, who (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to winne in that
Court of Rome the credit of a good Churchman, or to breede the more awe of
himſelfe in his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or being (as he is) Biſhop of
<hi>Vicenza,</hi> where the Canon was apprehended, to hold vp his owne
Iuriſdiction, with what preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice ſoeuer of the State where he was born)
holdeth faſt as it ſeemeth, the eare of the Pope to his ſecret
inſuſurrations. And as it vſually commeth to paſſe, that where there
is one hole already made, there euery ſmall touch wil make the ſame vvider
and teare it out farther: So fell it out in this breach or <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14581:6"/>
contention: for now are the Venetians fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther catched at, and looked into, for
former offences againſt the Church, to make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a broader irruption, and
ſcandall vpon them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are charged with the retention of <hi>Decime</hi>
due vnto the Church; and for their ill affection toward their Cleargie in
keeping them downe generally as much as may be.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they had paſſed an Act in the Councell of the
<hi>Pregati,</hi> whereby is directly forbidden the leauing of any land to Holy
vſes; ordering further any ſuch Legacie to be immediatly ſold.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the State hauing in penurious times taken money of
certaine Churches and Hoſpitals, at vſe of fiue or ſixe <hi>pro
Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> refuſeth nowe to reſtore the principall, tending that it hath
bene repayed in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe cauſes added vnto the firſt, and malignantly vrged to
his Holineſſe, were ſo diſtaſtful, and ſo diſtempered his
affections, as that ſhortly after, (hauing this grudge ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14581:6"/> heauy and vndigeſted) about Ianuary, in the time of
<hi>Marino Grimani</hi> then Prince, he commanded the <hi>Venetian</hi>
Embaſſadour then reſident at Rome, from his preſence, forbidding him
further acceſſe, while the State which hee ſerued ſtood in termes of
contumacie againſt the Church; And then with conuenient ſpeede, (the
ſting of this complaint ſtill egging on his ſharpneſſe) he directed
vnto the <hi>Venetians</hi> a <hi>Monitoriall Breue,</hi> (as they call it)
ſummoning them to obedience, and in defect thereof, menacing Excommunication
of the whole State.</p>
            <p>This admoniſhing Briefe was by the Popes <hi>Nuntio</hi> not
onely defended and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in publique, but with his Oratory fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
recommended, as ful of wiſe and louing moderation, Sith, by giuing vnto them
both fatherly aduiſe, and reſpit of repentance, it was rather an Argument
of indulgence in his Maſter, then of any furious precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Leonardo Donato</hi> (now Prince) at 72. yeres of his
age, was preſently elected to goe in quality of extraordinary
Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14581:7"/> to the Pope, of whom (being ready to
depart) the death of the former Prince made a ſtay, (not as if ſo vrgent a
buſineſſe of the State, had giuen way to his priuate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement, but
becauſe this accident did bring with it, a neceſſary excuſe of
deferring their anſwere to the ſummons, till they had made choice of
another Prince,) all conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ceaſing in the time of the vacancie.
Howbeit (this ſo ſolemne Embaſſage thus accidentally reſpited) It
being thought fit in the meane while, to apprehend and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all reaſonable
meanes in <hi>Rome,</hi> by the friends of this Rebublique, to remooue the
Popes indignation with conuenient le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; It prooued all of ſo little
effect, that it rather turned into further exaſperation, partly, through the
Popes naturall tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in whatſoeuer hee hath once reſolued, (which is
a note of him in his Court,) and partly, by the cunning of the firſt
inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, (who ſtil kept a watch ouer him in that buſineſſe;) but
principally, by the fore-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed cauſes themſelues, which in their
owne nature, and pondered according to <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14581:7"/> the grounds of that
religion, doeth not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any diſpenſation in ſuch an occaſion, where
no qualifying can bee vſed, without notorious affront and preiudice to the
Popes Authoritie.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, (after it was diſcerned that theſe cooling
mediations by interceding friends ſo ſlenderly preuailed,) The State of
<hi>Venice</hi> and their new Prince <hi>Leonardo Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> (who as a
priuate man for many yeeres hath had great credit in that State) elected for
Embaſſage toward <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Caualiere Dodo,</hi> whom they
furniſhed and prouided with good reaſons for the iuſtification of the
State; Namely, That concerning all thoſe foure points, wherein they be ſo
blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with diſobedience toward the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they haue
ſufficient and iuſtifiable allegations, out of common reaſon, Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
right, and priuiledges Authenticall.</p>
            <p>And ſpecially for the firſt, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to pricke the
very maſter veine, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining and correcting the vncleane
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of their licentious brood of ſingle fornicatours, and was
otherwiſe moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſiue, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14581:8"/> as moſt derogatory to
the Popiſh chalenged exemption and preheminence. For which were deliuered two
reaſons: Firſt that ſome of the Popes predeceſſours haue granted a
power vnto them, to proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forme of their Secular Courts
againſt the Cleargie of their owne Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>In delictis atrocibus.</hi>
(of which nature theſe muſt needs be accounted) Secondly, that they did not
by any their iudiciall atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or proceedings, inhibite or impeach the
Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction: But ſeeing that their immediat and
competent Iudges through fauors, negligence, or conniuence, omitted their
dueties in ſuch criminall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; that they were bound, both for the
conſeruation of their State, and by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Law, not to leaue malefactours
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Dodo,</hi> whom as a very choice man of great worth and
wiſdome, they had (as their manner is) choſen by their balls, to the
compoſing of this buſineſſe, was alſo further inſtructed in ſome
circumſtantiall cariages, As by faire ſpeech of their profeſſed zeale 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14581:8"/> vnto the Church and his Holineſſe, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage his
angry and ouer-vehement inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; And to finde out and purſue any likely
meanes of ſauing the Popes reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvhom they might perceiue to be the
more ſtiffe and vntractable, becauſe he had proceeded ſo farre already,
as that he could not hanſomly make ſtop or goe backe.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, to paſſe ouer that impediment and obiection,
deuiſed by the Factors and followers of the Pope, obtruding to the
<hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> as a preſident what they ſhould doe, the State of
<hi>Genua;</hi> (Who hath lately in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things ſatisfied his
Holineſſe,) that therein a difference might bee ſought out, and
inſiſted vpon, betweene the caſe of this Common wealth, and that of
<hi>Genua,</hi> (ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe to the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo
ſubiect and obſequious) which example the <hi>Venetians</hi> much
ſtomacked, and are very ſenſitiue of the compariſon with that
preſident.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Caualiere Dodo,</hi> being in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to depart
for <hi>Rome,</hi> it was thought fit to ſound firſt, whether he ſhould
be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with all circumſtance, according to the <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14581:9"/>
dignitie of the State, being afraid of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſcorne, and meaning to
proceede in this buſineſſe, from point to point very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, as
pretermitting no preciſe regard, And taking aſſurance either directly
from <hi>Rome,</hi> of good acceptation in plaine deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red termes, or
comfortably preſuppoſing the ſame by a conſtruction (which might
eaſily take holde of mindes well inclined) becauſe the Pope had ſince the
Monitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſent to them a congratulatorie Briefe (vvhich perhaps vvas his
complementing with the new Prince,) which they recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as ſome ſigne of
his relenting. They diſpatched <hi>Dodo,</hi> vvith opinion that their iuſt
Arguments would bee allowed of. He had as Aſſociate in theſe affaires,
the then Embaſſadour reſident, that with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of both their
aduiſes and labours, the deſired effect might bee the eaſier attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
vnto. Notwithſtanding all the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and forwardneſſe of both theſe
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the Pope like to a ſhrew, the more earneſtly that hee was
inſtanced, the more croſſely hee gaue his anſweres; And in 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14581:9"/> the end became ſo ſtately, as he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no more
debatings or entreatings, but with a Papall ſternneſſe hee proceeded to
the publiſhing of his Excommunication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this whole State, though in
the ſame he made a reſeruation of ſeuen and twenty dayes for
repentance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Venetians,</hi> after notice taken of this extremitie,
(finding ſo ſmall likelihood of reducing the raging paſsions of the Pope,
to ſuch a pacification as might ſtand with their contentment and
reputation) began to take vnto them ſuch confidence &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as both
the goodneſſe of their cauſe, (which was nothing elſe but the execution
of Iuſtice) and the honour of their State, (which hath not vſed to ſtoupe
with baſe obſequiouſneſſe) could worthily inſpire them with.
Wherein that you may knowe how their ſpirits did preſently ſparkle, and
were ſet on fire, by the tidings of theſe ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, they forthwith
publiſhed in the chiefe places of the City by ſound of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, a
Proclamation to this effect, <hi>That whoſoeuer hath receiued from Rome any
Copy <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14581:10"/> of a Papall Interdict, publiſhed there, aſwell
againſt the Law of God, as againſt the honour of this Common-wealth,
ſhall preſently render it vnto the Councell of Tenne, vpon paine of
death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, I pray you, let me make bold to obſerue vnto you by way
of a Parentheſis, (which I haue hitherto ſpared to interpoſe for feare of
interrupting the contexture of the Storie) that this ſo graue, iudicious, and
moſt aduiſed Senate, deſteineth and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Pope, euen for his
ſpirituall vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by laying vpon him the publike note of hauing
erred againſt the word of God it ſelfe, and that in a Conſiſtoriall and
Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall concluſion (as the Schoolemen terme it) and that they ſticke
not to reward with death the publiſhers of the Popes Bull of Interdiction:
Wherein, for that (to my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) they doe ſpeake <hi>verbatim</hi>
our Engliſh Lawes, holding conſent with vs by the very directions of
Reaſon, I would haue our Engliſh Catholiques (for by a Popefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion they
will needes vſurpe that name) to know that the King of Great BRITAINE, 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14581:10"/> and that Nation, hath better cauſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and
execute death againſt Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors in that kinde, then the <hi>Venetians,</hi>
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and at all times obliged to the Lawes and gouernment of that Church
of Papall ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>But I muſt go on with their other paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and proceedings,
which (to bee a true witneſſe vnto them) were all in euery cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
very ſutable and approoueable. In the beginning of May, (after mature
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, &amp; conſtant reſolution to vphold the Rights of their
Magiſtracie, together with their right proceedings, vnculpable, and not
ſubiect to any iuſt exception,) they concluded in Senate, vpon the
compoſing and publiſhing of a Proteſtation, in anſwere of the Popes
curſing, or curſed Bul; Which being conceiued, and expreſſed both for
forme, and matter, ſo exquiſite, as that any my interpreting, amplifying,
or abreuiating thereof, might diminiſh or deface the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which in it
is natiue, I do ſend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with vnto you, truely copied for your more diligent
peruſall.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14581:11"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="protestation">
                        <head>LEONARDO DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATO BY THE GRACE of God Duke of
<hi>Venice,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                        <head type="sub">To the moſt Reuerend Patriarkes,
Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, of all our Dominions of VENICE, And to all Vicars,
Abbots, Priors, Rectors of Pariſh Churches, and other Prelates
Eccleſiaſticall, <hi>Health.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath come to our knowledge that the <hi>17.</hi> of
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill laſt past, by order of the most holy Father Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the
fift, was publiſhed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed in <hi>Rome</hi> a certaine <hi>Bull</hi>
thundred out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, our Senate and Dominion, directed to you, of ſuch
Tenor and Contents as therein appeareth. Whereupon finding our ſelues bound
to preſerue in peace and Tranquillitie the State which God hath giuen vs to
gouerne: and to maintaine the Authoritie of a Prince that in 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14581:11"/> temporall affaires acknowledgeth no Superiour vnder the
Diuine Maieſtie; We by theſe our publique letters protest before God, and
to all the world, that we haue not failed to vſe all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes to
make his Hol. capable of our moſt ſtrong and inſoluble Reaſons. First,
by our Ambaſſadour Lieger with his Hol Then by our letters, reſponſiue
to Briefes written by him; and finally by a ſpeciall Ambaſsador ſent for
this very purpoſe. But finding his Hol. eares ſhut vnto vs, and ſeeing
the foreſaid <hi>Bull</hi> to haue bene publiſhed againſt the forme of
all reaſon, and contrary to that which the diuine Scriptures, the doctrine of
holy Fathers, and the ſacred Canons do teach vs in preiudice of the ſecular
Authoritie giuen vs from God, and of the libertie of our State, with
diſturbance of the quiet poſſesſion, which by Gods grace our faithfull
Subiects vnder our gouernement hold of their goods, honors and liues, with
vniuerſal and grieuous ſcandall of all: Wee doubt not a whit to hold the
foreſaid <hi>Bull,</hi> not only for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and vnlawfull, but alſo for
annulled and of no value, and ſo without force, fruſtrated, and vnlawfully
thundred, <hi>De facto nullo Iuris <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14581:12"/> ordine ſeruato.</hi>
Wherefore we haue reputed it conuenient to vſe againſt the ſame ſuch
reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as our Anceſtours and other Souereigne Princes haue vſed with
Popes, that haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the power giuen them by God for edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, beyond
their limitts: Eſpecially being perſwaded that by your and other our Loyall
Subiects, and by the whole world it ſhall bee ſo held and reputed:
Aſsuring our ſelues, that as you haue hitherto attended to the Cure of
ſoules of our faithfull Subiects, and to the Diuine Seruice, which through
your diligence flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth in this our State no leſse then in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
ſo you will hereafter continue in the ſelfe ſame paſtorall care. It
being our most ſtedfast Reſolution to continue in the holy Catholique and
Apoſtolique faith, and in the obſeruance of the Holy Romane Church, euen as
our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſsours from the beginning of the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Citie till
this preſent by the grace of God haue done. And wee will that theſe our
Letters for the vnderſtanding of all men be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed in the publique places
of this our Citie, and ſo of all other Subiect to our Dominion, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring
our ſelues that ſo manifest a publication <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14581:12"/> will come to
the eares of all ſuch as haue had knowledge of the foreſayd <hi>Bull;</hi>
and alſo to the notice of his Hol. whom we beſeech our Lord GOD to
inſpire that hee may vnderſtand the Nullitie of his <hi>Bull,</hi> and of
other his Attempts againſt vs, and that hee taking knowledge of the Iuſtice
of our cauſe, we may be encouraged to obſerue our Reuerence to the Holy Sea
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, of the which we and our forefathers, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with this
Common-wealth, haue beene, and will be euer most deuoted.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Giuen at our Ducall Palace</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>the ſixth of May in the fourth Indiction.
1606.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>Giacomo Girardo,
<hi>Secretarie.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>THis is to be noted, that before the publication of this
<hi>Proteſta,</hi> they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Popes <hi>Nuntio</hi> to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
and gaue him knowledge thereof; where it being pronounced before him, by a
Secretary of State <hi>Exſcripto</hi> (as is vſuall) <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14581:13"/>
he craued a ſecond view thereof, in the next roome: which being granted him,
after he had changed countenance at ſome things much diſpleaſing him, he
tooke his Prieſts cap, and ſtriking himſelfe therewith vpon the right
thigh, brake foorth into theſe words, <hi>Io ſo che ſi (ô Papa
Paulo</hi> 5.) <hi>che ti vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliono vbidire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for a matter of better note, and more memorable, I commend
this vnto you, That in the <hi>Proteſta</hi> (as in all other Actes of the
State ſince the ſaid 17. day of April) there hath bene ſeene ſuch
vnitie, not onely of Iudgement, but euen in paſsion among them, that one
onely ball did faile in the whole Senate, which yet was not in the
<hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue</hi> boxe, but in a boxe of a newtrall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſuſpending
the aſſent of the party.</p>
            <p>After the ſolemne publication of this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta,</hi> the
Embaſſadours departed on both ſides; The <hi>Nuntio</hi> firſt, and
with leaue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and granted, ciuilly and eaſily: but the
<hi>'Venetian</hi> Reſident at <hi>Rome,</hi> was thence ſent away with
violence. For the Pope by a Biſhop commaunded him to bee <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14581:13"/>
gone, vnleſſe hee would remaine there in priuate qualitie. The
<hi>Caualiere Dodo</hi> was before returned by order from the State. Their owne
moderate proceeding with the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> matched in compariſon with the
harſh, &amp; ſplenetike diſcharge of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, maketh that
ſending away of him, to be almoſt as ill taken, by all degrees of people in
<hi>Venice,</hi> as the very Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The State here is ſo ſetled and animated, as that on all
ſides, yong and old, rich and poore, Gentlemen and Artificers, are hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
fully reſolute, to mainteine againſt the Pope their owne actions. They
conſider not onely of their preſent detriment, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any
diſaduantagious, or diſhonourable end, but alſo of the future
conſequencies, if they ſhould giue head, and addition of ſtrength to the
Eccleſiaſticall authoritie, which already ſeemeth ouerſwolne and too
bigge, to all the wiſer Princes and States of <hi>Italy.</hi> And beſides
they do readily diſcerne, that in this controuerſie, the Pope will
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine more loſſe and ſhame then they; As <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14581:14"/> was
very grauely ſet foorth in a pretty tale, very pertinently told by a
diſcreet Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in a deliberation concerning this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; Who
told them, That by the Popes menaces, hee was put in minde of a nephew which he
had, who was wont to draw from his brother (being a tender father) all his
ſatisfactions, by threatning that otherwiſe he would turne Frier, or
ſeeke his fortune in ſome ſtrange Countreys, or the like: Till one day
lighting on his father in a wrong humour, and ſwearing, That vnleſſe hee
might bee preſently furniſhed with a good ſumme of money, (whereof hee
pretended want) he would precipitate himſelfe downe the ſtaires; His father
put it to the triall what he would doe: but the youth ſeeing it was now come
to the queſtion of his owne ſafety, went downe the ſtaires very quietly.
So, ſaid he, will the Pope doe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this heat of words, and
preſent diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, when hee ſhall come to conſider ſomewhat
cooly, that in proceeding againſt vs, <hi>Ginochera il ſuo &amp; non il
noſtro.</hi> This o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of his was much applauded, as very 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14581:14"/> probable, (if the diuulging had not caried the matter too
farre, and paſt returning to ſecond cogitations.)</p>
            <p>The very vulgar ſort doeth diſcourſingly lay foorth and
diſcipher the Popes inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateneſſe in this ſo hard a courſe of
his iniuſtice. They commemorate the many binding benefits of their State
collated on the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> And particularly for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and
demonſtrance, how much that Church is to them obliged, (if there were no
other teſtimony) They do in one notable matter of the triumph which Pope
<hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the third had in this Citie ouer the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<hi>Fredericke Barbaroſsa,</hi> both remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the greatneſſe of their
owne merite, and exprobrate the vnexcuſable ingratitude of that See. In this
very place, That Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror who had chaſed the Pope out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and
ſcant left vnto his Holineſſe any one hole for the Foxe to hide his head
in, was himſelfe brought, or rather wrought to ſo baſe a degree of
humiliation, as that he was firſt ſtouped to the kiſsing of the Popes
toe, and after, his head and necke was trode vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14581:15"/> by
thoſe vnholy preſuming feet, whileſt in a ſcorning and inſulting
glory, his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made bold of this Text, <hi>Super aspides &amp;
baſiliſcos ambulabis, &amp; conculcabis Leones &amp; Dracones.</hi> I
truſt that that ſinne of the aſsiſtance and adherencie of this Segniory
in that ſhamefull trampling vpon Imperiall Maieſtie, hath bene pardoned,
and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not in any <hi>debet</hi> vnto this day. They ſpare not alſo
to make particular reckoning of the great wealth and vaſt ſummes, which by
the colour of his Eccleſiaſticall headſhip is fetched from them to the
Popes Coffers. But eſpecially, they ſpeake of their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance from the
beginning of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Citie, in the obſeruance of the Rites
and Religion of the Romane Church. By all which and much more, as euery mans
fancie or diſpoſition ſerueth him, they doe amplifie the ingratitude,
iniuries and indiſcretion of their holy Father.</p>
            <p>This matter hath ſtirred vp the induſtrie and ſharpneſſe
of many that were idle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: The Politiques, how to contriue, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate,
excuſe, delay, preuent, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent: <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14581:15"/> The Canoniſts,
how to finde diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for the Conflict when it commeth to Diſputation:
The Oratours, how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime copiouſly; and the Hiſtorians, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
credibly theſe extreme wrongs: The Poets, how they may out of their ful
pennes raine foorth ſhowres of wit in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The Diuines, how to bee
conuerted to a new Religion, which point was ſubdiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into one of theſe
two reſolutions; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to force their Prieſts to ſay Maſſe after
Excommunication, (as if either the Pope were <hi>Nullus,</hi> or his Sentence a
<hi>Nullitie</hi>) or otherwiſe to paſſe to the Greeke faith, like vnto
diſplaced or diſcharged ſeruants or ſouldiers, that vpon their
caſsiering muſt ſeeke a new Maſter or Captaine.</p>
            <p>There is a generall liberty giuen for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulging of Diſcourſes
and Tranſlations; amongſt which is put in print the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
<hi>Gerſon</hi> the Chancellour of <hi>Paris,</hi> vpon the inualiditie of
the Popes Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, and ſome ſuch like conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Saint
<hi>Bernard</hi> to that purpoſe. For the more free publiſhing of which and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14581:16"/> the like Treatiſes, the Inquiſition hath been
ſuſpended by particular Warrant of the State; And when once the fludgates
were thus ſet open to all ſuch writers, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were pent and
reſtrained, to deliuer freely to the world, either defenſiue matter, in
iuſtification of this cauſe, or offenſiue tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to blemiſh and
blame the Pope for his temeritie; It is ſtrange to ſee what ſundry
ſorts of gybing and biting <hi>Paſquils</hi> were let fly abroad in
deriſion of his Holineſſe. But, amongſt the workes Apologeticall
ſagely and iudiciouſly written, Frier <hi>Paulo</hi> hath in a ſet
Treatiſe compoſed by him, not onely defended the <hi>Venetians</hi> from
this Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication and demands, but alſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points leſſened the
Authoritie of the Pope, by ſound allegations, &amp; by the proofe of
priuileges appertaining of right and in dignity vnto the State: whom it is
ſaid, that this Commonwealth hath rewarded for his labour with a good
penſion yeerely during life. And I haue likewiſe met with another
intelligence, That there is on the other ſide made out a ſecret
proceſſe againſt him, by <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14581:16"/> the Church, for his
infidelitie and treachery therein. Nay, a later newes hath here ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, That
this Frier <hi>Paulo</hi> hath bene ſince ſolemnly (by his image or
picture) burned at <hi>Rome,</hi> and reproched alſo by a ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
appellation of a <hi>mezo Lutherano;</hi> Such and ſo hote a fire of the
Popes wrath, hath blazed foorth againſt him. But the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> on
the other ſide, (to vphold him in comfort, and make him amends in glory,)
haue out of their grace and contemplation of his well deſeruing, dignified
him with a better choſen title of <hi>Theologo deſignato;</hi>
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing thereby the nature of his merite to haue beene this, Euen the
opening vnto their darkened vnderſtandings, ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary trueths in
Diuinitie, tending to the diſcouery of the falſe pretences of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
Supremacie. This high Attribute, from ſo Iudicious and Illuſtrious a
Senate, is (in the ſtead of his image reported to haue beene conſumed with
flames) like to a goodly or gilded ſtatue, which ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his name
and memory, in all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding times.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14581:17"/>It is to bee remembred, that the Popes
<hi>Interdict,</hi> did prohibite all the Religious to celebrate diuine
Seruice, or to exerciſe any Miniſteriall function among the
<hi>Venetians,</hi> whileſt they perſiſted in their contumacie. And the
Pope by further order called away the <hi>Ieſuits, Theatines,</hi> and
<hi>Capuchines,</hi> from among them, as if he meant to fire them all when hee
had once reſerued or preſerued them. The Pope conceiued (though in deed hee
was deceiued) that no ſooner ſhould his Papall indignation, and the
ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of his Excommunications be ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but that the people would
haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently rebelled, and the Churchmen haue ſtreight retired
themſelues. But the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> making a concurrence of their
Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Wiſedome, to maintaine the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of their
Iuſtice, &amp; nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the bleſsing and operation of Gods
Spirit, to giue thereunto anſwerable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, Decreed and commmanded
<hi>ſub poena furcae,</hi> as they would anſwere it at the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that
no Eccleſiaſticall perſons ſhould relinquiſh or deſiſt from his
charge or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14581:17"/> at the Altar, or ſhould depart out
of the dominions of the Segniory without order or leaue. Whereby in plaine
trueth they tread our ſteps, by ioyning vnto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie the Supremacie
ouer perſons Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall.</p>
            <p>They cauſed alſo to appeare before them all the Priors of
Pariſhes, and Superiors of Cloiſters, to receiue of them their promiſe of
faith. The Friers of <hi>S. George</hi> haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented their Reuenew, which
is <hi>of good value,</hi> to the ſeruice of the Prince. Others haue
anſwered, That howſoeuer they haue had their habite from the Pope, their
fleſh put them in minde of an other duety, and clapping their handes vpon
their naked armes, teſtified that they were diſpoſed to liue and die in
the ſeruice of <hi>S. Marke,</hi> and the State of their Countrey.</p>
            <p>The Prior of <hi>Saint Martins,</hi> hearing the Proclamation
afore inhibiting the hanging vp of Bulls vpon the Church, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the
deliuery of them to the Councell of Tenne, (if may ſhould be found,) ſaid
he had rather bee excommunicated twelue <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14581:18"/> yeres, then hang
halfe an houre. Others haue proteſted, that ſeeing they finde the
difference betwixt the Segniorie and the Pope, to be for matters onely of
Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that the Pope ſeeketh his particular profit, and not
that of IESVS CHRIST, they be reſolued to aduenture all with their
vttermoſt powers and conſtancie, vnder the obedience of the Common
wealth.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the vnanimous and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſolution,
aſwell of Eccleſiaſticall as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and generally of the whole
Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, to imploy their goods and life, to maintaine their libertie, and
approue their fidelitie, againſt the vniuſt, and haughtie pretences of the
Pope. And the Segniorie vſeth all diligence poſsible, to keepe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
vnmouable in ſo godly and bleſſed inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, certaine orders of their Churchmen are hence
departed, The The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atines, and Capuchines, by licence and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
relinquiſhment. The Ieſuits were the firſt that did begin to ſwarme,
and ſeeke further for a new hiue, but they were ſent <pb n="33" facs="tcp:14581:18"/>
away by courſe of expulſion, and open ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment out of the whole
dominion, and that by a ſpeciall decree, not ſo much for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to
continue the ſacrifice of the Altar, (which at the firſt they had giuen
ſome hope that they would do notwithſtanding the Popes Interdict, vnto whom
they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to bee as true and helpfull as his very life blood,) as for
other weightie Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, And among the reſt, for the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous abuſe
of that great inſtrument of State, Auricular confeſsion. And although they
haue beene before baniſhed out of diuers other Countries by Acts of
Parliament, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, as whereſoeuer they come will touch the quicke
and eate to the core) yet ſurely, neuer were they from any place diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded
or throwen out with more reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contumely then from hence. They were
ſuffered to carrie with them only their Quotidian habite and Breuiaries,
<hi>cum via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico</hi> to ſupport their neceſsities in their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile.
There was an inuentory taken by an vnder Secretary and Commendatore, of the
goods left behinde them, and ſeaſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14581:19"/> by the
State, rather for curioſities ſake, to know what they had gathered, then
for any meaning that the State hath euer to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for any part
thereof. The value whereof in certaintie of ſumme, if you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect I ſhould
relate, I anſwere they met with a concealement, and ſo it is vſed, being
a reſerued ſecret not yet made knowen: but if they haue kept their vow of
pouerty, as regularly as the reſt of their Society doth in other places, you
may well gueſſe that they were in that point no more beggars, then in their
other rule or vow of chaſtitie they bee ouer honeſt.</p>
            <p>In which ſearch haue bin diſcouered two memorable things:
Firſt a <hi>Scrinio</hi> (as they call it here) with partitions of their
addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to and from all parts, As <hi>England, France, Spaine,
Flaunders, Germany, Poland, Ruſsia, &amp;c.</hi> with ſubdiuiſions alſo
of the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into Townes, as <hi>London, Paris, Lions, Rome &amp;c.</hi>
And in this <hi>Scrinio,</hi> they had leſt rather through vanity, then
haſt, a great and incredible heape of the very aſhes and tynder of their
diſpatches. The other was <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14581:19"/> an artificial furnace, ſuch
as the <hi>Italian</hi> Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmithes doe vſe for the diſſoluing of gold
and ſiluer, which was brought into the Councell of Tenne, and hath bred much
diſcourſe; the beſt opinion being, that it was to melt the chaines,
rings, and iewels which they got from Gentlewomen, and ſo <hi>(Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata
ſpecie)</hi> to put them away in Bullion.</p>
            <p>Now, before their going, one of them reckoning himſelfe the
principalleſt, would needes alſo ſhew himſelfe the boldeſt: for
hauing obtained a priuate acceſſe vnto the Prince, made offer vnto him, of
interpoſing his Society, for the reconcilement of the Pope. Whereunto hee
receiued from the Prince this Noble anſwere, That the State of
<hi>Venice</hi> had neuer before vſed ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and would not
now beginne, And therefore hee willed him, to forbeare the imployment of
themſelues, either much or little, in this matter, and rather to ſpend
their time, in conſidering that they had bin alreadie too buſie in the
world.</p>
            <p>Me thinkes I heare him further tell them, that they might better
beſtow themſelues in <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14581:20"/> heauenly Meditations, then in
Negociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with States, and that they ſhould rather abound in ſpirituall
contemplation, enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>in Scrinio pectoris,</hi> then in ſuch
enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing traffique about ſecular buſineſſe, wherewith their
<hi>Scrinio</hi> of enterchanged aduertiſements was ſo fully fraught.
Laſtly, that they ſhould rather haue had melting and relenting hearts to
powre out foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of teares for the ſinnes and errors of the people, than
thoſe melting furnaces to conuert their fraudulently extorted rings or
chaines into wedges of gold: Therefore be packing hence you practiſers of
iniquitie, and proude Politicians that endeuour the rearing vp of your owne
greatneſſe, with the ruines of your Countrie that hath fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered you,
ſhall no more claſpe about this flouriſhing tree to raiſe and
encreaſe your own faction, by pinching and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtocke whereby you
be ſupported.</p>
            <p>Since their departure many things haue beene propoſed for their
perpetuall excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the placing of other Religious in their Colledge,
the depriuation and loſſe of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14581:20"/> to him that
ſhould euer ſpeake in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of them, and laſtly, to raſe the ſayde
Colledge and conuert it to ciuill vſes. What courſe herein will be held, it
is as yet vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided: but on all ſides, the State reckoneth it ſelfe well
ridde of ſuch pernicious Statiſts, that bee the Enginers and Pioners for
the Pope, working vpon, and againſt all, Princes and States, with their
practiſing plots, to bring them to their, either ſubmiſsion or
ſubuerſion, and their Maſter to his ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt exaltation.</p>
            <p>Thus haue they let the Kytes flie, and I truſt they will ſo
deſtroy their neſts, as that they may ſooner make their flights to the
furtheſt <hi>Indians,</hi> (there amongſt theſe Saua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to practiſe
their extreame ſauageneſſe, whereof the ſayd <hi>Indians,</hi> haue
already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a ſowre taſte) then to neſtle, or to bee nouſeled any
more in this Region. And let vs Engliſh alſo make hereof this vſe and
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance, That if the <hi>Venetians</hi> (clad in the ſame liuery of
Religion) hauing not any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and expreſſe particularities of their
trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable complottings to accuſe them of, yet <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14581:21"/> haue
iudged their very profeſsion, and the generalitie of their dealings, not
agreeable or ſufferable in a well inſtituted Common wealth; How much more
are wee bound by the Law of Nature and Nations, with all care and prouidence to
ſeeke to expell, abandon, and keepe out ſuch pernitious inſtruments, whom
we haue in all our try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of any Treaſon, from time to time, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
proued to haue bene the ſeed-ſowers, and the firebrands of all contriued
and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended miſchiefes? Therefore <hi>Exeat ex vrbe Catilina:</hi> For we
feare not ſo much the Popes open hoſtilitie, as we doe the enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings
&amp; circumuentings by ſecret practiſes. Hee cannot gaine from vs by any
forcible meanes, ſo much as the worſt haire vpon the body of any Subiect;
Then let him not by the conueyance of his poyſon, (through theſe Snakes)
into the boſomes of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, bereaue our body Politique of ſo many
worthy members, by alienating their hearts from their ſincere obedience.</p>
            <p>But left you may tell me, that my paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make mee to forget
my paſſages for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14581:21"/> proceeding in this Relation,
I returne to the declaring of that which remaineth, which is the Ciuill and
militarie prouiſions of this Segniorie. They haue bene here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed by
good intelligence, that the Pope is preparing of Forces, and ſeeking
confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, to tame their contemptuous inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies (as he termeth it)
purpoſing, if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring them to their former ſubiection, to bring
vpon them vnexorable Warre, and mercileſſe diuaſtation. Therefore out of
their prudencie, they haue alſo inclined their cares to the like courſes of
preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Some offers of aide and adherencie haue beene made vnto them, by
their confederate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by the mouth of Embaſſadours there reſiant,
whether ſeriouſly and by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or for faſhion and
complementally, I thinke they can ſcant tell: But they goe on confidently,
and with good conceite of their owne ſtrength. There is a Generall made by
Sea, and <hi>A Prouiditore de terra ferma,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Lieutenants
general of the <hi>Italian</hi> foote &amp; horſe. Into ſeuerall Townes are
asſigned the principall leaders of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14581:22"/> vnder
their pay, eſpecially in ſuch places as frontire <hi>Milan,</hi> or confine
with the <hi>Ferrareſzes.</hi> Thirtie new Gouernours of Galleyes haue beene
choſen. The principall Townes and Communities aſſured by a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of
ſolemne tenour, drawen by the Prince himſelfe. A Gentleman and Citizen
balli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here in euery <hi>contrada,</hi> by whom twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiuemore are to be
choſen againſt ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine caſualties, that might happen in the night in
this ſeate of their Dominion. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally they ſeeme ſo excited in courage
and confidence, as if they euen longed to pull him out of his Chaire, whom they
haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready caſt out of their hearts, and as if they were no leſſe
reſolute to bee reuenged of him, then he was proudly vniuſt to offend
them.</p>
            <p>And howſoeuer in the dependencie of this buſineſſe, many
things haue bene done here prouiſionally, ſome by aduiſe, ſome in
diſtemper, ſome in earneſt, ſome in ſport, ſome reſpectiuely,
ſome with contempt; yet hath nothing hitherto beene diſcerned to be done in
feare: Hauing caried euery cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:14581:22"/> (if my weake
capacitie may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to cenſure ſo graue a State) with moſt exemplar
wiſedome and magnanimitie, that we may conceiue hope, that GOD will by ſuch
beginnings, open an entrance for his trueth to get in to them, that haue long
ſlept in errour and eaſe.</p>
            <p>To paſſe on by following the tract of this buſineſſe
ſo farre as wee finde the ſame to haue bene driuen, I muſt tell you of
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chiefe Actor that hath ſtepped on the Stage to ſhewe himſelfe in
this Scene. It ſeemed fit to adde encouragement vnto his Holineſſe, and
to hold him on in the courſe of his former feruencie, whereupon ſundry of
his Cardinals, and other great Clearkes attending about him, with much
vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie incited him to an vnrelenting conſtancy againſt the
vnconformable <hi>Venetians.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom Cardinall <hi>Baronius,</hi> a
princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall man, of great name and note in that Court, addreſſed vnto the
Pope his horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory letters in that behalfe: whereof (for that I truſt and
intend ſhortly to ſend the ſame vnto you) I wil forbeare to rehearſe
the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14581:23"/> and regardable points: Onely that you may
know it by a true marke whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you may otherwiſe fortune to ſee it,
you ſhall haue thereof the firſt and the laſt words; wherein if you doe
finde ſound Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, and Texts of Scripture well applied, know that a
Cardinall is the Authour, who perhaps hath a kind of copartnerſhip with the
Pope in that prerogatiue of neuer er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. It beginneth thus: <hi>Duplex est,
beate Pater, miniſterium Petri; Paſcere &amp; occidere. Dixit enim ad eum
Dominus, Paſce oues meas: audiuit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> è coelo, Occide &amp;
manduca.</hi> The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of Peter, holy Father, is of two ſorts; To
Feed and to Kill. For the Lord ſaid vnto him, Feed my ſheepe: and hee heard
from heauen, Kill and eate. From <hi>Occidere,</hi> that is, Slaying or
killing, &amp;c. he inferreth the Popes power of Excommunication: how
ſtrangely or ſtreiningly, let the Diuines iudge: I promiſed you only a
narration, and therefore will not be bold in any refutation. It concludeth
thus, <hi>Memor eſto te in Eccleſia poſitum eſſe in Petram, in quam
omnes qui of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendunt, confringentur.</hi> Remember thy ſelfe 
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14581:23"/> to bee placed in the Church as a Rocke, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the
which whoſoeuer ruſheth, ſhalbe broken to pieces. Howſoeuer this making
of the Pope a <hi>Petra,</hi> be much beyond their former titles of deriuation
from <hi>Petrus,</hi> yet that application or rather amplification, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
well for an apt perſwaſion, to keepe the Pope to an vnfainting
reſolution.</p>
            <p>How far this Letter, or other the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſings, haue caried
the Pope in his inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of holding his hardeſt hand, or of ſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the ſtrength of his arme againſt this Segniorie, it is not readily to be
affirmed: but this I can further aduertiſe you of, that the ſeuen and
twentieth day of reſpite giuen to the <hi>Venetians</hi> for to returne into
their bonds of obedience, by giuing to his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſome ſatisfaction,
expired on Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday, and that it was then expected, that the Pope on
the Munday following, would haue performed his blacke ceremonies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to
the actuall fulmination of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdict before mentioned. But there was
<hi>Nullus ſtrepitus, &amp; nihil turbarum,</hi> no thing was done in that
buſineſſe, in ſo much as <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14581:24"/> (the expectation of
people being fruſtrated by ſuch omiſsion) it occaſioned much
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of voyce and rumour, according to the many ſundry coniectures
made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Some were of opinion, that his Holines (with a kinde of
faynting) was content to haue all to ſtand at a ſtay, till he could haue
ſome agreeable meanes offered, for clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auoyding of the vttermoſt
extremities. Some thought that hee would firſt conſider of, and prepare his
helps and aduantages, (which might concerne him to put in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,) and ſo
backe his formalities with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall prouiſion. Others, whether to
ſaue the Popes credit, or out of their knowledge and experience in the like
cauſes, affirmed, that any further acte on the Popes part was
vnneceſſary, ſith the firſt denunciation or promulgation of the ſaid
Interdict, ſtandeth of it ſelfe in ſufficient force: And that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the <hi>Venetians</hi> tooke no holde of the fauour aforeſayd, graunted vnto
them by way of reſeruation of the ſeuen and twenty dayes, they remained now
vtterly excluded from all grace, and were actually vnder the curſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14581:24"/>Thus this preſent Iune ſtandeth the
ſtate of this buſineſſe, more in expectation and preparation, then as
yet in any hoſtile acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and without any on either ſide, either
diſcernable yeelding, or open purſuit, The <hi>Venetians</hi> attending in
readineſſe what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtorme his Holineſſe out of the thicke and
black cloud of his diſpleaſure wil powre foorth vpon them: And the Pope
eagerly looking, that the beaſtes of the Forreſt will tremble when the Lion
roreth. Among the other neighbours that be lookers on, ſome perhaps are
ſetters on, to increaſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie; others gazers on, keeping
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a direct neutrality; ſome it much concerneth to ſtop the
courſe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; ſome with hollow intentions may plot on their
owne drifts; All, though they differ in their particular affections or
caria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, yet concurre in admiration of this acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, with a diſcerning of
the finger of God and his diuine prouidence, not to be pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated into by our
humane imbecillitie.</p>
            <p>But what will be the iſſue and euent of this great ſtirre,
it is onely knowen to him, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14581:25"/> who is the firſt ſtirrer of
all cauſes, and vnto whoſe fore-concluded endes, all the drifts and actions
of men are but ſubordinate. Yet for that it is a cuſtome in humane reaſon
to coniecture probably, where it cannot define a certaintie; I wil not ſticke
to acquaint you with the Iudgements of the wiſer and moſt experienced men,
that by precogitation do diſcourſe the ſucceſſe of this buſines.
Some thinke that the Pope will firſt yeeld, when he ſhall finde that hee
hath intricated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
into a trouble, which bringeth vnto him aſſured loſſe, and is not to
bee purſued without extreme coſt. Others, that the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> wil
be eaſily perſwaded to ſubmit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pope, and returne into his
boſome for grace, ſith they before ſo effectually la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured their
reconcilement, and haue not yet diſſeuered their Iudgements in the
que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Religion. Some are of opinion, that they may bee accorded by
this middle courſe, that the Pope may grant one thing, and they agree to an
other, by way of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation; that ſo each of them hauing in ſome ſort
their minds, they may apprehend <pb n="47" facs="tcp:14581:25"/> a ſatisfaction in part,
to be accepted for the whole. Some argue that the troubles of <hi>Hungarie</hi>
will call the Popes conſiderations that way, being arriued to a great
deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and inſolencie in their rebellious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Moſt men doe
directly thinke, that it will finally reſolue into a Schiſme, becauſe it
cannot well be diſcerned, how either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can giue ground or relent,
without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraging or abaſing of their eſtimation. Some of more
piercing inſight, and expert knowledge of courſes vſuall at ſuch times,
doe doubt that in concluſion it will prooue nothing but the further in
riching of a Popes Nephew, or one of his brothers, or of ſome vehement
Cardinall, for working of this ſame feate of flexibilitie, in the Popes
ſtiffe conceite and diſlike of the <hi>Venetians.</hi> Others do
contemplate aforehand the ſedulitie and deuotion of many well affected,
(though ſuperſticiouſly zealous) who doubtleſſe will not be wanting
with any their ardencie, to compoſe this controuerſie, were it but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
for feare, leſt the <hi>Turke</hi> doe take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by ſuch
diſſentions to aduantage and <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14581:26"/> aduance himſelfe in
Chriſtendome, or for ſhame, that we whom they account ſo vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of,
ſhould reioyce to behold their ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting contentions among themſelues.</p>
            <p>If you giue me leaue to tel what I thinke, Truely if the Pope
ſhould be ſo perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> as hee hath beene
euermore maliciouſly buſie with vs in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (where yet his
Authoritie hath ſo long beene out of date) hee would make ſhort worke vvith
them. Hee would giue away their Lands and Territories vnto ſome high
Potentate, (that muſt fight the Popes bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels) who with cruell incurſions
and Inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, euen by the ſword and Conqueſts, ſhal ſpoyle and
ſubdue them, till they fall on their knees for his Fatherly compaſsion. And
may hee not iuſtifie his ſo doing? Be they not Excommunicate? and ſo
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to be executed and proſecuted by the Secular arme, which it
ſhall pleaſe his Holineſſe to implore or imploy? (Wherein certainely as
a Secular prince himſelfe, he is likely to put in alſo his arme or foot
among them;) Nay, muſt not then the Leaguers <pb n="49" facs="tcp:14581:26"/> by the oath
of <hi>Trent</hi> combine their whole powers againſt the denounced enemies of
the Church? If <hi>Venice</hi> now had bene in his regiment Monarchicall, vnder
the rule of one abſolute King, Hee ſhould haue bene ſure to haue had good
ſtore of bad practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, vpon his perſon and againſt his life; And
perhaps (for ought that I know,) ſuch particular aduenturers, authorized in
ſuch Actions by their diſmiſsion from obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and incitation to
ſuppreſſe their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, may draw their warrants from this title of
<hi>Seculare brachium,</hi> imployable at the Popes call: But where there be
ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Senatoriall gouernours, they can hardly be at once ſurpriſed
with ſuch hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, if they can but take warning from vs, to
preuent the danger of <hi>The vault Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proſecute this Theame, What the Pope may do in his malice,
let vs out of our feeling be ſtill the exemplary inſtance. Can the Pope in
<hi>Venice,</hi> where his doctrine is wholly receiued, and where he hath ſo
long bene an adored Idoll, make no ſide or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14581:27"/> to
raiſe among them ſeditions vprores and inſurrections? <hi>England</hi> is
taught by experience what he can doe, where being (I ſay not a ſtranger,
but) an anowed enemie, yet hath hee ſtil enterpriſed to make a part, for
the ſtirring of tumults &amp; Commotions; And hath all this bene done
againſt vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>England</hi> ſo farre off? And wil he ſleepe
or let ſlip any opportunity to recall, recouer, or recommand <hi>Venice?</hi>
Well, if his heart or his meanes doe not ſerue him, to follow them with
enforcements of fierceneſſe, Do you thinke that he will not as eaſily
become a Foxe to ouertake them with kindneſſe, as he would haue played the
Lion by terrors and compulſion? Hath hee in <hi>England</hi> (by ſo many
fawnings and deprecations) ſought to draw vs againe into his Imbracements,
that are diuided from him by a broad ſea of difference in many points of
Religion? And wil he not in the cauſe of <hi>Venice,</hi> which hath ſo
long bene his darling, and as yet but by one parting channell diſſeuered,
(which may eaſily bee ouerſtridden) vnbend his brow from his heauie frowne,
and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14581:27"/> his appeaſed countenance? O that the
Honourably minded <hi>Venetians</hi> would put him to it, and trie his
diſgeſtion! That they would holde themſelues to their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and
ſhake off his ſhakels! If he doe but let it be a queſtion till it be
ſtudied and looked into in <hi>Venice,</hi> it will aſſuredly breed more
diſciples againſt him in one yere, then twentie ſucceſsiue popes
ſhall bee able to weed out.</p>
            <p>I hope it hath already euen in this courſe of a Table talke, and
by the defenſiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings which neceſsity hath conſtrained, ſo
faſtened in his mind a corraſiue, as (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the place) he may for
euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of an Vlcer in his pretended Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie; Then haue not I
reaſon to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he doth already euen longingly wiſh a kind
&amp; well formed reconcilement?</p>
            <p>The matter is, how to worke his purpoſe handſomely by ſome
cleanly carriage, As where his owne deſires importune him to concluding
termes, there vnder hand to procure himſelfe to bee much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14581:28"/>I haue very lately heard, that there is a
French Cardinall newly come to <hi>Rome,</hi> to beſtow his labour &amp; loue
in the according of theſe variances. What the ſucceſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will
be, wee muſt expect to heare hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: onely my conceit is, that no man of
any indifferent diſcerning, can be ſo ſimple as not to beleeue, that all
this ſo rough and high blowing contention, will well enough be on the Popes
part quieted and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated. Onely, it concerneth vs all, for the honour and
loue of the trueth, vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly to wiſh, that the eyes and hearts of the
renowned <hi>Venetians,</hi> may by the touch of Gods finger bee opened wider,
to let in the Lord of glory, bringing in his traine his trueth and
righteouſneſſe; and that their hands and puiſſance may bee ſo
ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an extraordinary addition of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, as that they may
from that nooke or corner of <hi>Italy,</hi> become as it were Gods har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bengers
to make way for him throughout that goodly countrey, to the ſuppreſsion and
demoliſhing of that ſo intolerable vſurpation. Which though wee may
rather <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14581:28"/> wiſh then hope for; yet reſpecting his
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence in theſe beginnings, we may with erected mindes attend the
manifeſtation of his further ordinance, in the euent which his wiſedome and
Iuſtice ſhall bring forth.</p>
            <p>And to ſuckle vp our hopes herein, with the opinion (at the
leaſt) of poſsibilitie, if not of better likelihoods, let England bee a
comfortable Inſtance, to cheriſh and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our thoughts from deſpairing
of a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull iſſue to the <hi>Venetians</hi> alſo. How many
yeeres, or rather ages, was England as it were in labour of this trueth, That
the Pope had no right in this kingdome to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, gouerne, command, or
cenſure any cauſes or perſons, Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall? How many
perillous throwes hath ſhee felt in her wombe and bowels to bring foorth this
child? what, how many, &amp; how migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie practiſes haue beene contriued to
haue deſtroyed this child within her belly, that it might neuer haue ſeene
the light? It is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully to be prooued by many ancient Records,
whereof ſome are regiſtred in the Courts of Law, (of the which that learned
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14581:29"/> Knight Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> Atturney general to his
Maieſtie, hath made an exact and moſt iudiciall Collection) ſome be
remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Towre, as Acts and ſignitures of Princes, or of the high
Court of Parliament, ſome are kept in <hi>Archiuis</hi> of our Spirituall
Courts, which alſo affoordeth vs ſome <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigia priſtinae
libertatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this Nation almoſt at all times hath in ſome meaſure or
other ſought to deliuer into the world this her conception, (that hath liued
and growen great within her) againſt the Popes encrochings and intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
into this Kingdome, with his vnwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted and vnlimited Supremacie; If you aske
me why, or how the ſight and publique apparance of this Trueth, (like vnto
the birth of a childe) was ſo long deferred and hindered: Firſt, you muſt
know that it is a Lions whelpe, and <hi>nihil magnum ſubito naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur:</hi>
next, the Midwife TIME ſerued not nor lent not ſufficing ayd; but chiefly,
the great red Dragon, that with his taile drewe the third part of the Starres
of Heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.</note> ſtood before the woman
which was ready <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14581:29"/> to be deliuered, to deuoure her child when
ſhe had brought it foorth. For let this be obſerued as a <hi>probatum
eſt;</hi> This Kingdom did neuer make or enact any Law ſo forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ful
againſt the Pope or See of <hi>Rome</hi> touching any ſuch their vſurped
powers or pretended rights, whereof the edge and point was not ſtraight
broken or blunted, by a Counter-law made at <hi>Rome,</hi> That whoſoeuer
ſhould proſecute any of thoſe Lawes to execution, ſhould be and remaine
vnder the heauieſt curſe of their greateſt Excommunication. Whereupon,
the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the ſoules damnation (whereof thoſe times of blindneſſe
were ſo ſenſitiue and fearefull) preuailed more to ſuppreſſe and
annihilate all ſuch Statutes giuing them no effect, (as if they had neuer ben
borne) then any other reſpects of duety, either to the trueth or to our
Countrey, could giue them life or ſtrength. But that I may ſhewe you ſome
euidence for the proofe of that which I haue affirmed, I wil (ſo farre as my
memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wanting at this preſent my larger notes, can doe his office) giue
you a diſcerning <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14581:30"/> taſte of this trueth, concerning
<hi>Englands</hi> continued claime of her owne Imperiall rights, and her manie
prouiſions, decrees, and conſultations, tending to the renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or
abdication of any the Popes Intereſt or intermedlings in
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 14. yeere of K. <hi>H.</hi> 1. the Popes Authoritie was
ſo little eſteemed in <hi>England,</hi> as that it was come to that
paſſe, that no perſons were permitted to appeale to <hi>Rome</hi> in
caſes of Controuerſie. Their Synods and Councels about Eccleſiaſticall
affaires were kept, without ſeeking any his licence or conſent: And they
would not obey ſuch Legates as hee ſent, nor come to the Conuocations which
they held.</p>
            <p>In the 31. yeere of K. <hi>H</hi> 3. The Pope vnderſtanding that
diuers rich beneficed men in <hi>England</hi> died Inteſtate, he ordeined a
Decree, That the goods of any Spirituall perſons dying Inteſtate, ſhould
remaine to the Pope: which Decree (purporting the Popes oppreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
preiudice of this Realme and the ſuruiuing friends of the deceaſed) the
King in no ſort would ſuffer to take <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14581:30"/> place: And the
ſame King by his Letter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitorie did flatly forbid a talage of the
Cleargie, which the Pope about that time had required.</p>
            <p>In the 30. of <hi>E.</hi> 1. the Popes Peter-pence, being not his
due, but rather the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Almes, were denied to the
Pope.</p>
            <p>In the 17. yeere of K <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons pray the Kings
aſſent, to baniſh the Popes power quite out of <hi>England.</hi> And in
the ſame yeere vpon the Popes intruding of himſelfe to make a peace
betweene the King, and <hi>France,</hi> King <hi>Ed.</hi> ſent him word, That
if hee would mediate betweene them as a friend, hee would heare him; but in no
ſort if he intermeddle as a Iudge.</p>
            <p>In the 50. of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Commons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that all the
miſeries of the Kingdom come by the Popes vſurpation; beſeeching the King
(this being the 50. and the Iubile yeere of his Reigne) that hee would ioyne
with them to caſt him out, for that he doth not paſture but pill Gods
ſheepe.</p>
            <p>In the times of <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>H</hi> 4. and
<hi>H.</hi> 5. ſundry Statutes were made againſt then <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14581:31"/>
that out of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> obtaine or purſue any perſonall
Citations againſt the King or any of his Subiects, or that procure from
thence any impetrations and prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Benefices and offices of holy
Church. And for that (as I before declared) the Pope on the other ſide,
oppoſed to theſe Statutes his Interdicts and ſentences of
Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication againſt the obſeruers of the ſame: In the 13. yeere of
<hi>R.</hi> 2. the ſaid Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications alſo are ſo farre diſauowed,
as that for the maintenance of the Liberties of the Kingdome, and the dignity
of the State, it was ordained, That if any did bring or ſend within this
Realme, any ſummons, ſentence, or excommunication againſt any perſon,
for the cauſe of making motion, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or execution of the ſaid
Statute of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſors, he ſhall be arreſted, impriſoned, and forfeit
all his Lands and Tenements, goods and cattels for euer: and moreouer incurre
the paine of life and member: And a Prelate making execution of ſuch
ſummons or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to forfeit into the Kings hands all his Temporalties.
Neuertheleſſe, for a long <pb n="59" facs="tcp:14581:31"/> ſpace after (whether by
reaſon of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ciuill broyles in <hi>England,</hi> which ſcant
affourded any leiſure of thinking, much leſſe of proſecuting vpon this
cauſe, or for that the ſuperſtitious ignorance of thoſe times did
entangle or rather captiuate the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of our people) this point of
the rights appertaining and incident vnto the Royall power &amp; Maieſty of
this Imperiall Crowne, and of the Popes vnlawfull oppreſsions and
vſurpations within this Land, lay aſleepe, was ſilenced, and ſuffered
open wrong, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the latter dayes of K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. who, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
himſelfe by the conferences and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of his learnedeſt Diuines,
and by the aduiſe and aſſent of the whole State aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in
Parliament, fully and finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided this queſtion, with the abſolute
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and extermination for euer out of this Realme and the Dominions
thereof, of any the Popes Authoritie and Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Thus hath God his prefixed periods for the producing at the laſt
of that trueth which hee oft ſuffereth his Church to be long in trauaile of:
Then why ſhould not <pb n="60" facs="tcp:14581:32"/> we likewiſe reteine ſome
comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of Gods accompliſhing and bringing to an happy effect
of that worke in the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> State, (though <hi>ſenſim &amp;
gradatim</hi>) whereof hee hath, of his prouidence and goodneſſe (and by
occaſions which for the iuſtice thereof may expect his bleſsings) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
and layd ſo likely groundworkes?</p>
            <p>ANd now (my good friend,) for a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing concluſion to this my
ouerlong letter, (as remembring wherefore I ted this tale) Lend me a little
more of your gentle patience, whileſt I draw out of the freſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
of this Relation, ſome ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory vſe, for the iuſtification of the
Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and the Iuſtice of our Magiſtracie,
from the ſcandalous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of crueltie, in our proſecutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
our profeſſed Aduerſaries tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Politicall and poenall
Ordinances. Which I will compriſe in a compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene our Engliſh
proceedings, with theſe of the <hi>Venetians:</hi> not intending at this time
to ſort out for them any other example or <pb n="61" facs="tcp:14581:32"/> preſedent,
then what I here haue already with my beſt iudgment wel obſerued, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
that if I ſhould poſt through <hi>France, Spaine, Italy,</hi> and all
<hi>Germany,</hi> to collect proofes &amp; demonſtrations to that purpoſe,
it would be as to me a labour ſupereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, ſo to them (whom nothing
will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie) like a charme to a deafe Adder.</p>
            <p>It cannot be obſcure to the whole world, That our Royall
kingdome hath for many yeeres together, quite expelled the Pope with his
Supremacie and ſuperſtition, where the <hi>Venetians</hi> (for any thing
yet of publique note) haue not fallen from him in any point of Religion, no not
diſauowed his gouernance or Supremacie in cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, but
onely excepted againſt his intruſion into the right of their owne
Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, in cauſes on their part iuſtifiable by all humane and
Diuine rules. Yet haue they reſolued vpon, and purſued courſes, no whit
inferiour in rigour and extremitie, to the ſharpeſt Lawes made with vs, in
ſo long a time, and after ſo manifold and violent occaſions. Yea, though
the matter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <pb n="62" facs="tcp:14581:33"/> vs in the deepeſt degree, euen of
<hi>(vter eſſet &amp; vter imperaret</hi> both) our regall and Imperiall
rights lying at the ſtake, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with the Papall vſurpations, and
our Religion, Peace, Iuſtice and tranquillitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually infeſted
by the poſitions, oppoſitions, practiſes, and iniuries of the Romiſh
faction.</p>
            <p>You ſee the Commands, and prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the
<hi>Venetians,</hi> to be all accompanied with the terrors of death, which is
<hi>vltimum in malis.</hi> I doe not taxe or diſlike this their ſeeming
auſteritie: But I inferre, that as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie coacteth them to be
ſeuere, ſo that our Lawes being enforced from vs by the like coaction, haue
alſo the like defence of naturall reaſon and primatiue Iuſtice, in the
righteous directions whereof they and wee doe agreeingly concurre. What doe you
thinke they would doe, if they had once made a generall reuolt or defection
from the Pope, in all the controuerſed Articles of difference? Can you
imagine, that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus roundly, they would not againſt their aduerſe
part, and in the behalfe of the <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14581:33"/> States quietneſſe and
preſeruation, proceed proportionably? As the buſineſſe now ſtandeth,
I make no queſtion, but that in caſe that any one <hi>Venetian</hi>
ſhould be found to oppoſe againſt the current or ſtreame wherein they
be now caried, he ſhould ſo be ſuncke and confounded, as neuer to ſee
the Sunne againe.</p>
            <p>In one point I muſt confeſſe they haue ſtepped further
then we, (yet they may hold it to be Iuſtice too, that the profeſſors of
po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie ſhould be forced to pouertie) Wee haue neuer vſed againſt any
Subiects ſuch ſeazures and confiſcations of their goods, neither exiling
of them out of their natiue Countreys, without orderly and iuridicall Trials
and Conuictions. Neuertheleſſe, I condemne it not, that either feare of
danger maketh them ſenſitiue, or that apparance of danger be met withall by
wiſe preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but if our Gouernours ſhould driue the wheeles of
Iuſtice ſo furiouſly, as to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe and take from euery
dangerous or ſuſpected Subiect his whole Eſtate, thereby ſtripping and
clipping him firſt, and then <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14581:34"/> to ſend away his body to
ſeeke his heart beyond the Seas, whither himſelfe before had ſent it; How
clamorouſly, and with what horrible yellings would our Enemies cry ſhame
and vengeance vpon vs all?</p>
            <p>The trueth is, That there is no State or Body politique
whatſoeuer, that will not in very ſenſe of Nature ſeeke their beſt
meanes againſt repugnant and ſickneſſe-breeding humours, and either to
reduce them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, if it may be, or to rid them away by eiection when
that cannot bee hoped. And therefore (howſoeuer we may imbrace rather the
ſweete and well contenting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mercy, for which princes are
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) let vs giue leaue to the <hi>Venetians</hi> (in imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
their paterne the ancient <hi>Rome</hi>) to reſtraine by prouiſions, that
ſuch dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and deteſted enemies of the State, as the Ieſuits are,
ſhould liue amongſt them, and that <hi>ad confirmandam audaciam,</hi> yea
that they ſhould there, <hi>deſignare oculis ad interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> or beyond
all this, to bring in into their very bowels a Troiane horſe, with his belly
full of treaſons, murders, and all villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14581:34"/> to be
vnloden and let looſe among them, for their finall ruine and confuſion.</p>
            <p>In England, for that firſt the graue adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of the
whole State in their great Aſſemblies of Parliament, is but to giue
ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to Iuſtice; And next, aſwell the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of our dread
Souereigne, who, to his Diademe of Dignitie, vnſeparably conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the
Scepter of his Iuſtice; as alſo the true Nobilitie of ſo wiſe and
Honourable Counſellors, who doeth make publique Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice their <hi>primum
in intentione:</hi> all true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Subiects will reſt indubitably
ſatisfied of the integritie, equitie, and vprightneſſe of that
Gouernment. And for other car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping reproouers, or barking ſlanderers, let vs
<hi>obfirmare mentes,</hi> that whome we cannot content with honeſt reaſon,
them we may contemne with a diſdaining confidence.</p>
            <p>Here I will end this threed, which I feare I haue drawen out in
length ouer tediouſly: I doe craue your well accepting curteſie to
diſpence therewith: And I further promiſe you, that if you pleaſe to
vouchſafe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <pb n="66" facs="tcp:14581:35"/> of ſome endeuours on your part
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the new ariſing occurrences within your diſcouery, you ſhall
not faile to be plyed ſtill in this ſort with more of my loue and
diligence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:14581:35"/>
            <head>THE ANSWERE OF AN ITALIAN D<hi rend="sup">or.</hi> of Diuinitie, vnto a Letter
written by a friend of his, concerning the Briefs of Pope <hi>Paulus</hi> 5.
his cenſure publiſhed againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians;</hi> And vpon the
Nullitie thereof: <hi>Drawen out of the Holy Scriptures, the</hi> Fathers, and
the Catholique Doctours. <hi>¶ Tranſlated out of the Italian
tongue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost reuerend Sir, I haue read your Letter, and doe not a little
won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that when I was wont alwayes to receiue from you the first
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements of all occurrents (especially when there was cauſe to aske
my opinion in them,) Now when ſo many matters of greatest impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14581:36"/> are current in your Citie, you haue bene the last man that
certified mee thereof. And yet you require me to ſet downe my opinion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
theſe Briefs publiſhed againſt your Common wealth, and vpon the
proteſtation of the nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and inualiditie of the ſame, made for the
defence and maintenance of their reaſons.</p>
            <p>Albeit I know well the cauſes of this your ſlackeneſſe,
and may attribute it to the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the matter: though I know not what
ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſticks moſt in your minde; yet I will excuſe you by reaſon
of the extraordinary buſineſſe you alledge, and ſatisfie you in this as
I haue beene wont to doe. And I hope to doe it with that ſpeed which you
deſire, I being prepared thereunto by the exact conſideration and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
which I haue beſtowed in that matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie.</p>
            <p>I ſay then (if I vnderſtand it aright) that your deſire is,
to know if the cenſures publiſht by Pope <hi>Paulus Quintus</hi> againſt
the Segnior of <hi>Venice,</hi> be voyde and of no force, as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in
their proteſtations; that they being ſo, you may celebrate the Sacraments,
and doe your Offices in your Churches, as you did before the <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14581:36"/> publication of the ſaid cenſures, without any ſcruple of
Conſcience.</p>
            <p>To anſwere then plainly &amp; in order to theſe your
requeſts, I will include whatſoeuer may be ſaid in that matter, in
<hi>Eight propoſitions.</hi> The doctrine whereof as it ſhalbe far from
faction, or flatterie, ſo ſhall it be founded vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures,
the ſayings and expoſitions of the Fathers, and vpon the ſtrongeſt
force of trueth and reaſon, that no man but vpon peeuiſhneſſe ſhall
dare to contradict it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14581:37"/>
               <head>¶ The firſt Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He power that Secular Princes haue, &amp; the Pope alſo (as
a temporall Prince ouer the States and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces which he poſſeſſeth)
is granted vnto them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly from God <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the vnderſtanding and cleereneſſe of this
Propoſition, it muſt be conſidered, that Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; ſeruitude
wrs brought in by the Law of Nations. The command of the Prince &amp;
obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Subiect, is by foure meanes; that is, by Election, by
Inheritance, by Gift, or by right of Warre: So that all Princes which by any of
theſe foure meanes euer haue beene, or now are placed in the Throne of
Principalitie, are iuſt and lawfull Lords: thoſe, I ſay, which haue
Authoritie from God to command, to make Lawes, to exact Tribute, to Iudge, and
to puniſh Subiects, <hi>without any exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Doctrine is not mine, but the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, Chap. 13.</hi> yea it is the holy Ghoſts
doctrine, which ſpeaks <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14581:37"/> with his mouth, and writeth with
his penne, whoſe wordes are theſe, <hi>Omnis anima ſubdita ſit
poteſtatibus ſublimioribus, nam nulla poteſtas, &amp;c.</hi> Let euery
ſoule ſubmit it ſelfe to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the higher powers, for there
is no power but of God. Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this place,
ſaith, The Apoſtle doeth this to ſhewe that Chriſt brought not in his
Lawes to ouerthrow Policie, but to giue it a better inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, ſhewing
that this is a commandement to all both Clergie and Laity, which hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
in the beginning, ſaying, <hi>Omnis anima pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatibus ſublimioribus
ſubdita ſit, etiamſi Apoſtolus, Euangeliſta, Propheta, aut quiſquis
tandem fuerit:</hi> Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to higher powers, whether he
be Apoſtle, Euangeliſt, Prophet, or whoſoeuer. And for all that doeth not
this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection ſubuert pietie. Whereupon in the old Lawe, although the
<hi>Leuites</hi> had a high Prieſt that was <hi>Aaron;</hi> yet in temporall
things, cauſes, and iudgements, they were ſubiect to <hi>Moyſes</hi>
their temporall Prince, as <hi>Couuarruuias</hi> proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, <hi>Cap. 31.
quaeſt. prateca. Nu. 3.</hi> And in the Primitiue Church there was no
difference of Tribunall or Iudgement ſeate: for <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the
Emperour was the firſt which at the requeſt of the Biſhop of
<hi>Conſtantinople</hi> granted, that the Cleargie in Ciuill cauſes might
be iudged by their owne Prelates, without preiudice not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to
himſelfe. In which caſe, and in all criminall faults he left it ſo that
the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14581:38"/> ſhould be ſubiect to the Prince and to the
Miniſters of the Prince temporall, as is plainely to be read <hi>Nouell.
Conſtitu. 85.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither becauſe <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great ſaid to
ſome Eccleſiaſticall perſons preſented vnto him, <hi>Vos à
nemine iudicari poteſtis, quia ad Dei iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium reſeruamini,</hi> as
<hi>Gratian</hi> writeth, <hi>Cap. 12. quaeſt. 1.</hi> Can it bee gathered
that they be not ſubiect to ſecular Princes? for this was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
of that Emperor to ſhew himſelfe towards the Church benigne and deuote. But
it was not becauſe he thought ſo indeed: for if he had ſaid true, they
could not be iudged by Prelates neither, the wordes being <hi>ad Dei iudicium,
&amp;c.</hi> which would be a grieuous errour.</p>
               <p>The Clergie then as well as the Laitie <hi>(de iure diuino)</hi>
are ſubiect to the ſecular Prince. <hi>Omnis anima poteſtatibus
ſublimioribus ſubdita ſit;</hi> the reaſon is, that as none is excepted
from the obedience he oweth to God, ſo hee cannot be excepted from the
obedience which is due to the Prince: For as the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>Omnis
poteſtas eſt à Deo,</hi> for which Kings and Secular Princes by the
Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> are called Gods. <hi>Deus ſtetit in Synagoga Deorum,
in medio autem Deos dijudicat:</hi> for as King <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> declareth,
<hi>Lib. 2. Paralip. Cap. 19.</hi> The Secular Iudges, <hi>Non hominum, ſed
Dei iudicia exercent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame place Chriſt citeth in Saint <hi>Iohn, Cap.
10.</hi> and confirmeth, that the name of Gods belongeth vnto them. <hi>Si
illos dixit Deos ad quos <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14581:38"/> ſermo Dei factus eſt,</hi> as
<hi>Bellarm.</hi> learnedly noteth, <hi>Cap. 3. Lib. de Laicis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle goeth forward and ſayth, <hi>Qui poteſtati
reſiſtit, Dei ordinationi reſiſtit:</hi> behold here the Authoritie
that Princes haue to make Lawes vpon euery matter, which ſhall binde euery
perſon according to that which is read in the Prouerbs of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
where God ſayth, <hi>Per me Reges regnant &amp; legum conditores iuſta
decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt.</hi> Hence is it, that the Chriſtian Emperors,
<hi>Iuſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in the <hi>Code</hi> haue made
many lawes concerning Eccleſiaſtical perſons, their goods, and
gouernment, vnder the titles of <hi>Epiſcop. &amp; Cler. &amp; Sacroſanct.
Eccleſiis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe Lawes the Apoſtle commandeth obedience without
reſiſtance, becauſe they which ſhall make reſiſtance, <hi>Ipſi
ſibi damnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem acquirunt,</hi> that is, do commit mortall ſinne, wherein
if they die, they ſhall be condemned to the eternall fire of hell.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the Apoſtle commandeth to pay to the Prince Tribute
of euery thing, <hi>Cui vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, vectigal; cui tributum, tributum: ſunt
enim mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtri Dei ad tributa:</hi> which place the Angelicall Doctor
<hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> maſter of Diuines the ſonne of the Cath. ſchoole,
ſayth, That if the Cleargie be free from Tribute, they haue not that
Priuiledge (as ſome thinke) <hi>Iure diuino,</hi> but <hi>ex priuilegio
Principum,</hi> ſpeaking there of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Princes.</p>
               <p>Finally, I conclude with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for the 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14581:39"/> authoritie of the Prince, <hi>Non enim ſine cauſa
gladium portat, Dei enim miniſter ad vindictam:</hi> behold the authoritie of
the Secular Prince, <hi>Punire poena ſanguinis,</hi> which the
Eccleſiaſticall Prelats not hauing, (after they haue diſgraded
malefactors of the Clergie, and declared them vnfit for Eccleſiaſticall
degree) they can goe no further, but to haue them puniſht by death, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer
them to the Secular power. And that no man ſhould thinke, that his words were
words of counſell and not of precept; to make all ſure the Apoſtle
affirmeth, <hi>Ideo neceſsitate ſubditi estote non ſolùm propter
iram, ſed etiam propter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam:</hi> So that wee are bound in
conſcience to obey the Secular Prince in all things aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as we are
taught by <hi>S. Paul.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>¶The ſecond Propoſition.</head>
               <p>OVr Sauiour Chriſt, although as the Sonne of God equall to the
Father, is <hi>Rex Regum &amp; Dominus Dominantium:</hi> Notwithſtanding
beeing clothed with our mortalitie, neither before his death, nor after his
moſt holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection did hee exerciſe power as a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Prince.
Hee had no temporall kingdome, as he ſaid to <hi>Pilat,</hi> asking him,
<hi>Rexestu?</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Tu dicis:</hi> but though I be a King,
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>Regnum meum non eſt de hoc Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> that is, a
Kingdome temporall. Wherupon when thoſe people which were miraculouſly 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14581:39"/> fedde by him with fiue loaues and two fiſhes, would haue
made him a King, <hi>aufugit, ne rape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent eum, &amp; facerent ipſum
regem.</hi> Hee would iudge no man, for he anſwered to thoſe which would
haue had him giuen ſentence in one of their controuerſies, <hi>Quis me
conſtituit iudicem ſuper vos?</hi> yea hee acknowledged <hi>Pilate</hi> the
mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Caeſar</hi> for his iudge: <hi>Non haberes in me
poteſtatem niſi tibi data eſſet deſuper,</hi> as <hi>S. Thomas</hi>
noteth in the Epiſtle to the Romanes. Finally, he commanded that tribute
ſhould bee paide to the ſecular Prince <hi>Caeſar. Reddite quae ſunt
Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris Caeſari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some do oppoſe to this propoſition of ours, ſaying, though
Chriſt paied tribute to <hi>Caeſar</hi> for himſelfe and <hi>Peter,</hi>
yet he ſaid, that he was not bound to pay it, <hi>Nunquid filij debent
ſoluere tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butum?</hi> wherein (ſay they) he tooke vpon him the right of a
temporall Prince, who is exempt from tribute. To this is anſwered, that
thoſe of the Countrey (as ſome Doctors ſay) called by the name of
Children, were not bound to pay tribute, and he being of the Countrey, and
<hi>S. Peter</hi> alſo, he affirmed that he was not bound.</p>
               <p>Others to further contradict this propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doe alleadge,
that Chriſt did caſt out the buyers and ſellers of the Temple. Which is
anſwered, that hee did this as a Prophet vpon zeale: for to the like
purpoſe the Euangeliſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the verſe of <hi>Dauid, Zelus domus tuae
come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit me.</hi> Others ſay, that when he ſent his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14581:40"/> to bring him the Aſſe and the Colt, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them
to ſay to the maſter, <hi>Dominus opus habet,</hi> that is, The Lord of all
the world. But that place is not vnderſtoode to drawe from thence the
authoritie of a Prince, but to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that the Lord of heauen and earth
was ſo poore, that he was faine to borrow thoſe Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell (as ſome Doctors
doe expound it) the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, for that if hee would haue taken vpon him the
Authoritie of a Prince, he would not haue ſaid, <hi>Opus habet,</hi> but
<hi>Dominus ita praecipit,</hi> or ſome other ſuch like.</p>
               <p>To conclude, they which iudge this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of ours hard
to bee prooued, doe ſay ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally that Chriſt (when hee entred
trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly into Ieruſalem, the day of the Palmes) tooke vpon him the
Authoritie of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Prince: Whereupon the Euangeliſt alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the
prophecie, <hi>Ecce Rex tuus venit tibi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſuper aſinam &amp;
ſuper pullum filium aſinae:</hi> but hee that conſidereth the matter, may
perceiue that albeit our Sauiour was the promiſed King and Meſsias, yet
entring into Ieruſalem in that baſe and abiect ſort, he ſhewed not to
take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Authoritie of a Prince temporall, but rather as hee ſaid
to <hi>Pilate,</hi> that his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was not of this world, but ſpirituall
and eternall: for temporall Kings enter into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Kingdomes in
an other maner of Pompe, then Chriſt did ſitting vpon an Aſſe and an
Aſſes Colt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14581:40"/>
               <head>¶The third Propoſition.</head>
               <p>OVr Lord Ieſus Chriſt hauing neuer vſed the Authoritie of
a temporall Prince, it may not be ſaid that hee left this Authoritie to
<hi>S. Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors, which are his Vicars, ſeeing the
Vicar is neuer more then his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. Wherupon <hi>Soto</hi> treating vpon
this point, <hi>lib. 4. Sententiarum,</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine de
Autoritate Papae,</hi> ſay, that they wonder at the Canoniſts, that they
durſt without any reaſon or authoritie of the New Teſtament, affirme
<hi>Quod Papa ſit Dominus totius orbis directè in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralibus:</hi>
A doctrine indeede ill founded and ſcandalous. I know well that ſome
beſides the Canons (which as humane Lawes in concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie with the Diuine
can haue no equall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie) doe ſay that <hi>Tho. Aquinas lib. de
Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Principum, Cap. 10. &amp; 19.</hi> affirmeth the Pope to bee
<hi>Dominus totius Orbis in temporalibus &amp; inſpiritualibus.</hi> But that
Booke is not his, as Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſheweth, <hi>li. de
poteſtate Papae:</hi> For beſides other aſſured coniectures, this is
one, That in that Booke <hi>lib. 3. cap. 20.</hi> he makes mention of the
Succeſsion of <hi>Adolphus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour after <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> and
of <hi>Albertus</hi> after <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus,</hi> which were, the firſt Anno
1292. The ſecond 1299. And <hi>Tho. Aquinas</hi> died Anno 1274.</p>
               <p>They cite moreouer an other place of <hi>Thom. 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14581:41"/> Aqui. lib. 2. ſent. diſtin. 44.</hi> where he ſaith,
<hi>Eſſe in ſummo pontifice apicem vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poteſtatis,
Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; Spiritualis:</hi> But he that reads the Text may ſee that
<hi>Thomas</hi> was of a contray opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſaid that in matters
Temporall, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Prince ought rather to be obeyed then the Spirituall,
and in matters meerely Spiritual, rather the Spirituall then the Temporall; hee
concludes, that if it were not the Pope, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the Prouinces ſubiect
vnto him both Iuriſdictions, hee ought of his ſubiects to bee equally
obeyed in the one and the other.</p>
               <p>To weaken the force of this our Propoſition, ſome ſay that
Pope <hi>Alexander 6.</hi> diuided the Indies to the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi>
and of <hi>Portugale:</hi> Becauſe hee as Chriſts Vicar was the naturall
Temporall Prince therof, and that Pope <hi>Leo 3.</hi> gaue the Empire of the
Weſt to <hi>Charles</hi> the great by the ſame reaſon: But theſe men
are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much deceiued, ſith <hi>Alexander</hi> not as Lord of the Indies,
but as Compromiſſary Iudge ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted betwixt the Kings to appeaſe and
quench the flames of Diſcord, by ſentence determined that the ſeas
ſhould be diuided, and that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madoes of the one ſhould paſſe
through one of thoſe ſeas, and the other through the other, and that
whatſoeuer was gotten or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide <hi>Iure belli,</hi>
ſhould be the Conquerers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuiſion made by him, as the
Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians of that time report.</p>
               <p>Tis true that <hi>Leo 3.</hi> being chaſed from the 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14581:41"/> See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and reeſtabliſhed by
<hi>Charles</hi> the great, cauſed the people to proclaime him Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, as
<hi>Platin</hi> ſaith: which act the Hiſtorians doe attribute to the people
of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſeeing the Empire euill gouerned by the <hi>Grecians
Iure antiquo,</hi> did elect an other Emperour. Now they ſay that
<hi>Charles</hi> being Patron of the State, bought the title thereof of
<hi>Irene</hi> and <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> that were Emperours, and that
<hi>Irene</hi> &amp; <hi>Nicephorus</hi> were content therewith. In ſumme, be
it as it will, it is certaine that the Pope being driuen from his ſeat, and
being poſſeſſour of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, gaue no Empire to <hi>Charles,</hi> who
already <hi>Iure belli</hi> was Patron thereof. And that he gaue him the
abſolute title thereof, it is not a thing certaine: and if it were, yet it
may bee anſwered (aſwell in this caſe as in others alledged againſt our
Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that the Pope not hauing from Chriſt any authority in
Temporall things, (as hath beene, and ſhalbe ſaid more cleerely in the next
Propoſition) if hee haue taken to him any ſuch authoritie, or hath done it
by conſent of the intereſſed, or for that hee hath any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall power
by any of the foure meanes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd: yet for all this, hence it is not
proued that he hath direct authoritie in Temporall things from our Sauiour
Chriſt. And beſides, many things are done by many men, whereof if it be
ſought <hi>Quo iure</hi> they doe them, it will not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14581:42"/>
               <head>¶The fourth Propoſition.</head>
               <p>THe authoritie promiſed by Chriſt to Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
vnder the Metaphor of the Keyes, is meerely Spirituall. <hi>Tibi dabo claues
Regni Coelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> hee ſaith not <hi>Regni terrarum:</hi> and reaſon
teacheth that which is read in the Hymne of the Church, <hi>Non Eripit
mortalia, quia regna dat Coeleſtia:</hi> for the Temporall kingdome, and the
Monarchie was founded from the beginning, (by God the great Monarch of the
world,) in what ſort that ſhould bee gouerned. So that Chriſt our Sauiour
did not found the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie Temporall. It remayneth then to ſay that hee
founded the Spirituall, which is plainely ſeene in Saint <hi>Ioh. cap.
20.</hi> where he hauing ſaid, <hi>Omnis poteſtas data eſt mihi in Coelo,
&amp; in terra:</hi> yet giueth hee it to the Apoſtles, and amongſt them to
Saint <hi>Peter</hi> limited and with reſeruation. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufflauit in eos
&amp; dixit, Accipite Spiritum Sanctum: quorum remiſeritis peccata
remittuntur ijs, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum retinueritis retenta ſunt:</hi> where both by
the act that Chriſt doth, &amp; by the words he ſpeakes is gathered, that
the authority of the Pope is Spirituall, and ouer ſinne, and only ouer
ſoules, according to the wordes of that prayer of the Church to Saint
<hi>Peter, Qui beato Petro potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem animas ligandi atque ſoluendi
tradidisti:</hi> the which is limited, as is ſaid, yea the authoritie of
Excommunication giuen to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall, 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14581:42"/> 
                  <hi>Math. 18. Si frater tuus in te peccauerit, &amp;
Eccleſiam non audiuerit, ſit tibi ſicut Ethnicus &amp; Publicanus.</hi>
In the which place our Sauiour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth authoritie to Excommunicate, but the
ſinne, and obſtinacie in the ſinne preſuppoſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <head>¶The fift Propoſition.</head>
               <p>THe perſons and goods of the Cleargie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the power
of the Secular Prince, albeit ſome (I know not vpon what ground) hold that it
is done <hi>Iure Diuino:</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the contrary opinion (that it
is onely <hi>Iure humano</hi>) is the better, and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the
Diuine Scripture, to the holy fathers, and to the trueth of Hiſtories. For
(be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which we haue ſaid in the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that
Prieſts in the old Law were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Secular Prince, beſides that
<hi>Solomon</hi> depriued <hi>Abiathar</hi> of the Office of high Prieſt
amongſt the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> as is read in the <hi>3.</hi> Booke of the
Kings <hi>Cap. 2.</hi>) in the time of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church vntill the time of
<hi>Iustinian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, it is not read in the Law, of any priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of exemptio giuen to the Cleargie. <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ad tribunal
Caeſaris ſio, Caeſarem appello.</hi> And to leaue infinit other examples,
It is read in the life of <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour, That
he depoſed Pope <hi>Iohn 22.</hi> by his owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe he was a
moſt wicked man. And if the exemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be <hi>iure diuino,</hi> why would Pope
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14581:43"/> 
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt graunt, That <hi>Charles the
great</hi> ſhould haue auctoritie to chuſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome. Cap.
Adrianus &amp;c.</hi> which alſo <hi>Leo 8.</hi> did in fauour of
<hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, as is written in the ſame Diſtinction which is
the <hi>63. Canon in Synodo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This doctrine is not only of <hi>S. Paul</hi> as I haue proued
in the firſt Propoſition, but of <hi>S Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Tho. Aqui.
Soto</hi> that excellent Diuine. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 25. Lib. 4. Senten.</hi> of
<hi>Corrunias</hi> an excellent <hi>Canoniſt. Cap. 31. Pract. queſt.</hi>
who for his owne behoofe citeth Pope <hi>Innocentius 3. Alciat. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rareſe
Medina,</hi> and others. And theſe two do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors <hi>Soto</hi> and
<hi>Corrunias</hi> in this particular are much to bee eſteemed, hauing both
of them written ſince the Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> And their
demonſtrations are of exceeding efficacie: For beſides the Authoritie
affirmatiue of <hi>S. Paul, Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Thomas;</hi> and
beſides the vſance of the Primatiue Church, they bring two moſt forceable
negatiue Arguments, that is, 1. If the Clergie, and that which belongs vnto
them be exempted <hi>Iure Diuino;</hi> In what booke of the New or old
Teſtament, Or in what Epiſtle of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> or in what Goſpel are
they exempted? 2. The other is, that no Chriſtian Prince Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, looking
well to the quiet and good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his State, regards this at all, but
lets the Clergie enioy what exemptions hee pleaſeth, and what he pleaſeth
not, he ſuffereth them not to enioy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14581:43"/>
               <head>¶The ſixt Propoſition.</head>
               <p>WHilſt the Prince of <hi>Venice</hi> (lawfull and naturall
Lord of his State, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth no ſuperiour in Temporal things but
God) maketh Lawes concerning goods and poſſeſsions Eccleſiaſticall,
which are vnder his dominion, and puniſheth Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
in grieuous and haynous caſes, &amp; doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of ſuch goods, as
are not already paſſed to Eccleſiaſticall perſons by the Authoritie
which he hath immediatly from God, wherof he hath neuer beene bereaued, either
by Priuiledge granted away, or by Canon receiued, but is in poſſeſsion
thereof by an immemorable cuſtome of many, not yeeres, but ages, He ſinneth
not in ſo doing. The reaſon is, for that <hi>Qui non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit contra aliquam
Legem non peccat,</hi> Much leſſe can it be ſaid, That he ſinnes
<hi>Qui obſeruat Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</hi> And moreouer, <hi>Qui retinet quod ſuum eſt
non peccat.</hi> Neither are wee to be forced to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the opinion of them
which hold, That the exemption is <hi>De iure Diuino:</hi> for euery
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is free to follow what opinion he pleaſeth, ſo it be a
Catholique opinion. Nay rather to follow the opinion of a Doctour grounded
vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reaſon, againſt a torrent and forced opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doubtleſſe, is not
ſinne; As <hi>Nauarra</hi> well proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in his <hi>Praeludia.</hi> Then
ſhall it be no ſinne to follow the opinion of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and of ſo
many, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14581:44"/> and ſo famous Doctors, alleadged in the firſt,
and the fift Propoſitions. Nay to ſay true, I cannot excuſe them which
hold that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption is <hi>Iure Diuino,</hi> they ſeeming vnto mee
ſometimes ill grounded, ſometimes ill aduiſed, ſometimes too bolde,
ſometimes too flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proposition">
               <head>¶The ſeuenth Propoſition.</head>
               <p>WHileſt the Segniorie of <hi>Venice</hi> is not cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, nor
commits any ſinne in doing that which is ſpoken of in the precedent
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, if it be excommunicated by Pope <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Quintus</hi> his
Briefe publiſhed, &amp; if the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and holy places be thereupon
interdicted: the Sentence is of no force, not only by the law poſitiue,
becauſe the order preſcribed by the Canon, <hi>De ſent. Excom. 6.</hi> is
not obſerued; but alſo <hi>Iure diuino</hi> it auayleth not, becauſe the
au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Excommunicating is conditionate, <hi>Si peccauerit in te frater,
&amp;c.</hi> ſo that where there is no ſinne, Excommunication hath no
place; and a Sentence fulminated againſt him that ſinnes not, is no
Sentence for defect in the matter.</p>
               <p>Neither let any man be ſo groſſe of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to
thinke, that if the Segniorie (as is proued) hath not offended, neither doth
offend <hi>in retinendo quod ſuum eſt,</hi> that it doeth
neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe offend in not obeying the Pope, and <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14581:44"/>
perſiſting in their opinion. For conſtancie in a good opinion is not
obſtinacie: and he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends not, cannot bee termed diſobedient and
obſtinate, ſith hee which obſerueth the Law, doth a holy an meritorious
worke, and he that obeyes not in thoſe things which cannot bee commanded him
to doe, commits no ſinne at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="proposition">
               <head>¶The eight Propoſition.</head>
               <p>IT is true that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayth, that the
ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Paſtor, be it iuſt or vniuſt, is to be feared: but
this ſentence makes nothing to the matter. For there is great difference
betwixt the ſentence of an Eccleſiaſticall Iudge which is vniuſt, and
that which is no ſentence at all, as moſt learnedly affirmeth <hi>Nauarra
de Cenſuris Eccleſiasticis, Cap. 27. &amp; Soto 4. Sentent. diſt.
22.</hi> That the vniuſt cenſure is to be feared, but the cenſure that is
no cenſure is not to be regarded, therefore the Cenſures publiſhed by
Pope <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Quintus</hi> as is ſaid, being none at all, but like
Scrowles formed in the Water and the Aire, that is without foundation,
ſubſtance or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; I am of opinion, that you ought not to obſerue
them, neither that you ought to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate any thing in your Churches therefore.
For although <hi>Nauarra</hi> in that place recited, reaſoning vpon
Excommunication forceleſſe and nought, ſaith theſe wordes:
<hi>Sententia Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14581:45"/> Eccleciaſtici inualida ſeu
nulla, nihil aliud opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in fore interiori ſiue exteriori, quàm
quod obligat Execmmunicatum ad ſeruandam eam quoad populus ſibi
perſuadeat vel perſuadere debeat cauſas nullitatis propter
ſcandalum.</hi> Notwithſtanding this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine makes much for me: for the
cauſe of the nullitie is apparant to all the people of <hi>Venice,</hi> &amp;
if it were not manifeſt to all, yet all muſt needs know it by the Edict
which the Prince hath made to let euery man vnderſtand it: ſo that the
ſcandall is not onely not to be feared, but I ſay vnto you, that I cannot
excuſe certaine Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, who whether their error breeds of
ignorance, or of ſome ſiniſter affect, haue made choiſe rather to
depart from the Citie, then to goe forward to celebrate and Miniſter the
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments as they were ordained to doe by the Prince, both for the good of
the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and the Religion. <hi>Nam ipſi ſibi fuerunt lex,</hi> and
would not follow the example of the Cathedrall Church, and of all other holy
and auncient orders of Religious, nor of all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, vnto whom I will
ſay with Chriſt, <hi>Quòd expediret vt ſuſpenderentur molae
aſinariae in colla eorum, vt non ſcandalizarent puſillos meos</hi>
Beſides, to defende the libertie of the naturall Prince, who maintaines and
conſerues amongſt the people peace, libertie, and Religion, is a thing
<hi>de iure Naturae,</hi> that is as much to ſay, as <hi>Iure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino,</hi>
whereas ſentences Eccleſiaſticall are <hi>de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſitiuo,</hi> which
muſt yeeld vnto the other, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14581:45"/> when there is
queſtion of the Nullitie of them, whereupon ſome doe deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
which thinke that this controuerſie is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout matter of faith, ſith it is
onely about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p>So that Sir, you may go forward to celebrate and communicate,
and to doe whatſoeuer you did in your Church before the publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the
Cenſures, not only becauſe you write to me to be reſolued to do it, but
alſo to auoyd the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale; both becauſe a ſentence of no force is not
to be obſerued <hi>cùm conſtat de nullitate,</hi> and alſo that
you doe not ſeparate your ſelfe from your head (which is the Prince) in
controuerſies of Iuriſdiction which haue no ground of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Nay I am of opinion, that he which ſhall not heare Maſſe
at leaſt vpon the holy-day, ſhall commit ſin, their Sentence being of no
force, and it being celebrated in all places. <hi>Nolite ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere timorem
vbi timor non eſt, nolite trepidare, &amp;c.</hi> Let it not be ſaid of you
which haue beene alwayes faithfull to your Prince and to the Commonwealth, that
<hi>Filij matris meae pugnaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt contra me:</hi> but, obey the Apoſtles
precept, <hi>Omnis anima poteſtatibus ſublimioribus ſubdita ſit, non
ſolùm propter iram, ſed propter conſcientiam.</hi> This I ſay
not, becauſe I doubt of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie (perſwaded as I am of your
ſelfe and all others of that City, that you are moſt ready to ſpend your
liues for your Prince) but becauſe the iuſtice of the cauſe which is
manifeſt vnto <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14581:46"/> you, may be much more apparant by this my
anſwere.</p>
               <p>For a Concluſion let mee aduertiſe you, that although the
Segniorie of <hi>Venice,</hi> haue ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon paine of life, that all the
Religious keepe open their Churches, and proceed to doe their dueties as they
did before, yet haue they not done that for feare: But becauſe that Citie
hauing bin alwaies Catholike (and now more then euer profeſſeth to
conſerue it ſelfe ſo,) it will not ſuffer that in the exerciſes of
pietie there ſhould bee any change, or that the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion thereof
ſhould be occaſion of precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto any; which euill the Prince is
bound by all meanes to remedy, by the Law of God, for the intereſt of the
Church.</p>
               <p>Many other authorities and reaſons I could haue adduced in
this diſcourſe, which would haue made for me: But for the haſte you haue
made me make, and for the deſire I haue to vſe breuitie, I leaue them all,
reſeruing my ſelfe to write of this matter at large in a booke <hi>Of the
Supreame authoritie of a ſecular Prince,</hi> which ſhortly I will ſet
forth in the Latine tongue. In the meane time let me put you in mind that you
read the doctrine of that moſt ſound Doctor <hi>Nauarr:</hi> who in all
that is ſaid before is of our ſide, as in particular <hi>Cap. Nouit. de
iudicijs Notab. 3.</hi> and in his Manuel <hi>Cap. 27. de Cenſuris.</hi> And
to omit other particularities, that you retyre your ſelfe to that moſt
ſecure Port of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14581:46"/> doctrine, which teacheth
that all Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall perſons, if they enioy any exemptions, they
enioy them not <hi>de Iure diuino, ſed ex priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio principum.</hi> Which
Priuiledges do retract, diminiſh, and enlarge as pleaſeth them, when new
reaſons preſent themſelues vnto them, to doe it to the profit of the
Dominions ſubiect vnto them, euen as Popes doe with the Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of
Indulgences, and other things depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon their Spirituall authority, the
which they ſometimes annihilate, ſometimes dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, ſomtimes
increaſe at their pleaſure. And becauſe the doctrine which I haue
produced, is not mine, but all drawen out of the bookes of deuote and
Catholique Doctors; I wil adde no more now for the confirmation thereof. Our
Lord IESVS giue you Conſolation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
